<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-05-01T17:03:22+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Those Pesky Bugs! Blog</title><subtitle>Random rumblings of a software engineering who has a special talent for  introducing hard to catch bugs better than anyone else.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Interview preparations: Operating System vs Kernel</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/kernel-vs-operating-system.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview preparations: Operating System vs Kernel" /><published>2018-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-03-01T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/kernel-vs-operating-system</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/kernel-vs-operating-system.html">&lt;p&gt;Let’s talk about a kernel, an operating system, and all the differences between
the two. I’ll explain what happens when you turn on your computer, and when you
run programs. Computers, smartphones, even cars — operating systems are everywhere. It’s worth
knowing why we need this type of software, and what it does (other than taking
up that precious disk space).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1100/1*1qBb2G3QXlZUzPtN__Reog.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Almost all electronic devices run some kind of an operating system
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/photo/iphone-technology-iphone-6-plus-apple-17663/&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;why-do-we-need-an-operating-system&quot;&gt;Why do we need an operating system?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers changed quite a bit since the twentieth century when they were
invented. First computers could only run a &lt;strong&gt;single program&lt;/strong&gt; until it finished…
or crashed 😱&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each program used all of the available hardware and was responsible for all
standard tasks a computer had to perform. For example, &lt;strong&gt;every program had to
contain all necessary drivers&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Computers were not beginner friendly, to say the least.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keeping track of what program was supposed to be run next was done by humans.
Sometimes quite a bit of creativity was required:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;At Cambridge University the job queue [a queue of programs waiting to be
executed] was at one time a washing line from which tapes were hung with
different colored clothes-pegs to indicate job-priority.
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Operating_system#History&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And you’re complaining that your internet is too slow to stream Full HD videos,
huh? 🤣&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the complexity of software, demand, and the number of users grew, it became
too cumbersome and time-consuming to do all those things manually.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A program that could manage hardware, schedule program execution, and monitor
resources was needed. That software should:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Allow multiple applications to run at the same time&lt;/strong&gt;. Hardware resources (for
example, CPU time, network connections, opened files, and so on) should be
shared “fairly” between those programs.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Make sure that a buggy or malicious program cannot disrupt other
applications&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;kernel&quot;&gt;Kernel&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Kernel is an always-running program that has complete control over everything
in the system.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you power on your device (for example, a computer or a smartphone) a small
program called a &lt;strong&gt;boot loader&lt;/strong&gt; is executed. Boot loader is a very small
program — it starts the process of loading the operating system (including the
kernel) and finishes immediately afterwards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From then on, kernel is the king.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It decides what program will run next, and for how long.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It decides which memory can be used by each program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If a program wishes to use any input/output device (like a mouse, a keyboard,
and so on), it has to request access to that device from the kernel. If multiple
programs want to access the same resource at the same time, kernel decides which
program will get access first.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kernel makes sure that a buggy or malicious program cannot disrupt other
programs. It stops programs from monopolizing access to hardware, or modifying
memory belonging to other processes. If a program misbehaves kernel will kill it
😨&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kernel is very powerful, but it only provides a basic level of control over the
hardware it’s running on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/880/1*Vg893Xwy99b_N5V6S9L0nw.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Kernel is the king&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;operating-system&quot;&gt;Operating system&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In essence, a computer is just a tool we use to get things done. It has to be
easy to use and user friendly. Hence, we need features such as a graphical user
interface, a multimedia player, antivirus software, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An operating system (OS) consists of a kernel and additional software
providing those features&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What software is included in the operating system is entirely up to the creator
of that OS. This makes defining an OS very difficult so it’s often described as
“whatever you get when you order an operating system”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, Windows 10 offers:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a sophisticated kernel&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;graphical user interface&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;firewall and
antivirus software&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;web browser&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;multimedia player&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;small utility programs like a calculator, text editor, and so on&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;…and many other features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A kernel is an essential part of an operating system. It’s an always-running
program that is in control of everything in the system. It manages hardware
resources and program execution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An operating system consists of a  kernel and some additional software making
user’s interaction with his or hers device more pleasant. This might include
graphical user interface, shell, web browsers, and so on.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Let’s talk about a kernel, an operating system, and all the differences between the two. I’ll explain what happens when you turn on your computer, and when you run programs. Computers, smartphones, even cars — operating systems are everywhere. It’s worth knowing why we need this type of software, and what it does (other than taking up that precious disk space).</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Leaky abstractions, CPU cache …and why programming is fun</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/what-is-cpu-cache.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Leaky abstractions, CPU cache …and why programming is fun" /><published>2018-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/what-is-cpu-cache</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/what-is-cpu-cache.html">&lt;p&gt;Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code
works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts
can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 Let’s talk about
what is a CPU cache and why it’s important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/880/1*ISecwEffT-z73UDJ3IpPww.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During my computer science degree, I learned about basic building blocks of
electronic circuits, and how they can be used to build logic gates. Those logic
gates provide a &lt;strong&gt;layer of abstraction&lt;/strong&gt; that allows engineers to reason in
terms of logic operations, and not electrical currents and voltages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Logic gates  can be combined  to build a computer that provides us with another
layer of abstraction. It allows a programmer to think in terms of a set of
available CPU instructions and not just logic gates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Languages like Python allow programmers to think in terms of high level concepts
and not just basic operations the CPU supports — that’s yet another layer of
abstraction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/880/1*2x6n0n_2I7piSq8A-Sr35Q.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In computer science, more than in any other field, we have many layers of
abstraction that enable us to solve problems faster, without worrying about the
underlying implementation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But there is no such thing as a perfect abstraction. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.joelonsoftware.com/2002/11/11/the-law-of-leaky-abstractions/&quot;&gt;All abstraction
leak&lt;/a&gt;
at one point or another,  and we suddenly have to deal with the underlying
complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s one of the reasons programming is so fun… and frustrating. Concepts and
ideas interweave, sometimes making debugging very challenging — but also very
rewarding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;high-level-question-low-level-answer&quot;&gt;High level question— low level answer&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/880/1*yj8ZHxYczXzyaSuqqmbO-Q.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;An array (top) vs a linked list (bottom) — note how elements of a list are
scattered around the memory&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s look at an example — a high level problem. Let’s say you have to decide
between using &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@lukdomanski/interview-preparations-everything-you-need-to-know-about-lists-and-arrays-81093c140e78&quot;&gt;a linked list and an
array&lt;/a&gt;.
The main requirement is that iterating through elements has to be as fast as
possible. What do you think — which data structure will be faster?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The time it takes to iterate through all elements is &lt;strong&gt;proportional to the
number of elements&lt;/strong&gt; — the bigger the list/array, the longer it will take to
visit all elements. Quite intuitive, right?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From a high-level point of view, it should not matter if you chose to use an
array or a list. Both data structures should take more or less the same amount
of time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be surprised to learn that an array can be &lt;a href=&quot;https://stackoverflow.com/questions/36939141/why-use-lists-when-arrays-are-faster&quot;&gt;significantly
faster&lt;/a&gt;
than a linked list.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-whyyyyyyyyy&quot;&gt;But whyyyyyyyyy&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To understand why, we have to go down many levels of abstraction — we have to
investigate how the hardware you’re using works. First, we need to understand
what a &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CPU_cache&quot;&gt;CPU cache&lt;/a&gt; is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern processors are very fast in comparison to how much time it takes to
access main memory. To reduce the time it takes to access RAM, data that is most
likely to be needed by the CPU is placed in a memory that’s smaller, faster, and
located “closer” to the processor. We call that memory &lt;strong&gt;CPU cache.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine working in a grocery store that is getting its supplies from a big
warehouse. The warehouse can store a lot of stuff but it takes a while to find
and access things kept there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why every grocery store has a certain supply of all products (those most
likely to be purchased by customers) stored on its premises. You can’t store
that many things in the store, but they are  quickly accessible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is exactly how a CPU cache works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/880/1*jwPBgH1VX05BHhN8vrQBxg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Main memory is like a warehouse — it can store a lot of stuff but it takes a
while to access it&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;you-might-be-asking-how-do-we-know-what-data-should-be-stored-in-cache&quot;&gt;You might be asking: how do we know what data should be stored in cache?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A computer program is basically just a sequence of instructions to be executed
by the CPU. Those instructions are often accessed in order, one after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The same is true for arrays — we often iterate through them, accessing all
elements in order, one after another. If we’re accessing an element with an
index 5, it’s also likely we are interested in elements 6 and 7.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why memory addresses that are “close” to a recently accessed address are
more likely to be visited again. &lt;strong&gt;When accessing some memory, “nearby” segments
of memory should be place in cache as well.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;okay-that-is-interesting-but-what-does-it-have-to-do-with-our-data-structures&quot;&gt;Okay, that is interesting. But what does it have to do with our data structures?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s supposed that a CPU needs to access some memory address. First, it will
check if it’s available in the cache. If it is, then it can be accessed very
quickly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, if it’s not currently stored in the cache, we have to fetch it from the
main memory. We call that a &lt;strong&gt;cache miss&lt;/strong&gt;. Cache misses slow down the execution
of our code because accessing the main memory is relatively slow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since all elements in the array are stored as a continuous block of memory, when
reading an element with some index &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k&lt;/code&gt;, following elements (&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k+1&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k+2&lt;/code&gt;,
&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;k+3&lt;/code&gt;,…) will be cached as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;This leads to fewer cache misses&lt;/strong&gt; and results in better performance compared
to a linked list, as in a linked list elements might be scattered around the
memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To answer a seemingly simple question we had to dive really deep. We had to
understand what a CPU cache is and how it works.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I think we can all agree — programming never gets boring 😀&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 Let’s talk about what is a CPU cache and why it’s important.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview preparations: Introduction to arrays, lists and dynamic arrays (Part 2)</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/arrays-lists-dynamic-arrays-part-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview preparations: Introduction to arrays, lists and dynamic arrays (Part 2)" /><published>2018-02-04T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-02-04T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/arrays-lists-dynamic-arrays-part-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/arrays-lists-dynamic-arrays-part-2.html">&lt;p&gt;Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code
works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts
can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 In the previous part
of this article we introduced arrays, lists, and dynamic arrays. Now, we will look into
the operations they support and how fast those operations are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/1*r9JNNy7QnX-y5MWkaMPtcg.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the first part of the article we introduced three fundamental data
structures:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;an array&lt;/strong&gt; — a collection of elements stored in the memory as a single,
continuous block of data&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a list&lt;/strong&gt; — a collection of elements, each containing a link to the next
element&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;a dynamic array&lt;/strong&gt; — an array that is resized to fit all elements without
wasting too much space&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s compare those data structures. What operations do they support? How fast
are they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A basic understanding of time complexity and big-O notation is required as I use
them extensively. If you’re not familiar with those concepts, HackerRank has a
great &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=v4cd1O4zkGw&quot;&gt;video-explanation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s dig in!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;what-operations-are-supported-by-those-data-structures-what-is-their-time-complexity&quot;&gt;What operations are supported by those data structures? What is their time complexity?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(In this section I denote the size of the array as &lt;strong&gt;n&lt;/strong&gt;)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*uCv0HsVqM6l4QwyrzF-TDw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;array&quot;&gt;Array&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Vanilla” arrays are dead simple. We can:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;access an element given its index&lt;/strong&gt; — in &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; time. We know exactly where
each element is located in memory, so we can access it very quickly.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s all. We can’t add or remove new elements (arrays always have a constant
size).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;dynamic-array&quot;&gt;Dynamic array&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dynamic arrays are more interesting. As with “vanilla” arrays, given an index,
we can &lt;strong&gt;access a corresponding element in constant time&lt;/strong&gt;. Dynamic arrays also
support adding and removing elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adding an element&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;at the end of the list&lt;/strong&gt; — takes, on average, &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; time. Remember that
some insertions will take &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;at the beginning of the list, or somewhere in the middle&lt;/strong&gt; — takes linear
time. To insert a new element in the middle of the list, we have to “shift” all
preceding elements by one position (see illustration below). We have to copy a
portion of the array — &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; elements, so this operation takes &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removing an element&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from the end of the list&lt;/strong&gt; — takes, on average, &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; time. Again, some
insertions are slow and take linear time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from somewhere else in the list&lt;/strong&gt; — takes &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time. As with adding an
element in the middle, we have to shift all preceding elements — this time in
the opposite direction (see illustration below). Thus, removal will take
&lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*wY28q3YhRQjRDWvp5-ENiQ.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;linked-list&quot;&gt;Linked List&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a linked list, accessing an element with a given index &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; is a bit more
complicated. As we don’t know where that element can be found in memory, we have
to iterate through the list until we find it. This will take &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time.
That’s significantly slower than other data structures we discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lists allow adding and removing elements too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Adding an element&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;at the beginning of the list&lt;/strong&gt; - is just a matter of changing a few pointers, so it can be done in &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; time. We have to change the value of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;head&lt;/code&gt; so that it points to our new element &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NEW&lt;/code&gt; and set &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;NEW.next_element&lt;/code&gt; so that it points to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;A&lt;/code&gt; (see illustration below).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;somewhere in the middle&lt;/strong&gt; — can always be done in &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time. First, we need to find the spot where we want to insert the element — this will take &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt;. Inserting the element can be done in &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; time, so the whole operation takes &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; + &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; = &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;at the end of the list&lt;/strong&gt; — if we keep a reference to the last object, we can do this in &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt; time! Otherwise, we have to iterate through the entire array to find the last element. This will take &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time. Implementations of a link list typically include that reference to the last object to keep this operations quick.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Removing an element&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from the beginning&lt;/strong&gt; — takes &lt;strong&gt;O(1)&lt;/strong&gt;. As with adding the element at the beginning of the list, we only need to change a few pointers.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;from anywhere else in the list&lt;/strong&gt; — takes &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time. We have to find the element first (which will take &lt;strong&gt;O(n)&lt;/strong&gt; time) and remove it. To remove the element &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;C&lt;/code&gt; we change the value of &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;B.next_element&lt;/code&gt; so that it points to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;D&lt;/code&gt;. That’s it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it! You know quite a lot about arrays and lists now. You should probably practice some &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.geeksforgeeks.org/top-20-linked-list-interview-question/&quot;&gt;interview questions&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the third (and last) part, we’ll investigate why arrays can be significantly faster than linked lists when iterate through elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 In the previous part of this article we introduced arrays, lists, and dynamic arrays. Now, we will look into the operations they support and how fast those operations are.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview preparations: Introduction to arrays, lists and dynamic arrays</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/arrays-lists-dynamic-arrays.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview preparations: Introduction to arrays, lists and dynamic arrays" /><published>2018-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2018-01-28T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/arrays-lists-dynamic-arrays</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/arrays-lists-dynamic-arrays.html">&lt;p&gt;Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code
works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts
can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 Let’s talk about two fundamental data structures everyone needs to know:
&lt;strong&gt;arrays&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;linked lists&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*reYwnxuSVfy--DXjFgnjhQ.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Photo by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pexels.com/photo/businesswomen-businesswoman-interview-meeting-70292/&quot;&gt;Tim Gouw&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;so-what-are-arrays-and-linked-lists-lets-think-low-level&quot;&gt;So what are arrays and linked lists? Let’s think low-level.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An array is a collection of variables (or objects) that is stored in a memory as
a consecutive block of data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*htdnGT1LBPpiRMuw4sRkPg.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;myArray in memory&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When an array is declared, an appropriately sized block of memory is reserved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;An array has a constant size.&lt;/strong&gt; The memory “following” the array might be
already in use, so we can’t just make the array “longer” to store more elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each element in the array has some index &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; that tells us where the element is
in the array.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Element’s address (where it is located in the memory) can be easily computed. We
need the address of the beginning of the array (called &lt;strong&gt;base address&lt;/strong&gt;), and an
index &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;i&lt;/code&gt; of that element:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;element_address = base_address + i * element_size&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is important, because it allows us to &lt;strong&gt;quickly access any element with a
known index.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;An &lt;strong&gt;array is just a block of memory containing a number of variables or objects&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All elements are stored in order, one after another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, in a &lt;strong&gt;linked list&lt;/strong&gt; there is no particular order in which
list’s elements are located in memory: they might be non-consecutive and
out-of-order. This is because memory is allocated as we create elements, on
as-needed basis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*8ww-gpHZ-u7pJb1DTThWzw.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Linked list in memory&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a (singly) linked list each element is represented by:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;the element itself&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;a pointer &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;next_element&lt;/code&gt; (represented by arrows on the illustration) to the next
element in the list&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have to keep a pointer (usually called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;head&lt;/code&gt;) to the first element in the
list. Often, we want to keep a pointer (usually called &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;tail&lt;/code&gt;) to the last
element in the list for fast access. To summarize:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;pre class=&quot;highlight&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;Element contains:
   value - value/object we're storing
   next_element - pointer to the next element in the list

LinkedList contains:
   head - pointer to the first element in the list
   tail - pointer to the last element in the list
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;dynamic-array&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Dynamic array&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;arrays-always-have-a-constant-size-what-can-we-do-if-you-want-to-add-another-element-to-an-already-full-array&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Arrays always have a constant size. What can we do if you want to add another element to an already full array?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can: 1) create a new, bigger array, 2) copy all elements from the old array
to it, 3) add the new element at the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_array&quot;&gt;Dynamic arrays&lt;/a&gt; use this approach.
To add a new element:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A) If there is space in the underlying array — just add the element&lt;br /&gt; B) If
there is no more space for a new element — create a new, bigger array (typically
&lt;strong&gt;twice the size&lt;/strong&gt;), copy all elements from the old array, and add the new
element at the end (see illustration below).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/800/1*gIsT4ryqzI3_gaMgFjte3A.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Inserting elements into a dynamic array
(&lt;a href=&quot;https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/3/31/Dynamic_array.svg/289px-Dynamic_array.svg.png&quot;&gt;source&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Size&lt;/strong&gt; (or &lt;strong&gt;logical size&lt;/strong&gt;) is the number of elements that are stored in our
data structure. &lt;strong&gt;Capacity&lt;/strong&gt; is the maximum number of elements that could fit in
the underlying array. For example, on the illustration below, initial capacity
of the array is 2 and its size is 1.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are those… turtles?&lt;/strong&gt;😱&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice that sometimes inserting a new element happens very fast (case A), but
sometimes we need to &lt;strong&gt;copy an entire array&lt;/strong&gt; (case B). Thus, occasionally an
insertion will take longer (as indicated by those adorable turtles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How much longer? That depends on the number of elements in the array — copying
an array takes linear time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;That’s quite sluggish, isn’t?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, yeah, dynamic arrays are not &lt;em&gt;always&lt;/em&gt; fast. But those slow insertions are
not happening that often…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;It can be &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cs.cornell.edu/courses/cs3110/2011sp/Lectures/lec20-amortized/amortized.htm&quot;&gt;proved&lt;/a&gt; that &lt;strong&gt;inserting an element into a dynamic array takes, on average, constant time&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;wait-how-can-this-be-true&quot;&gt;Wait, how can this be true?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A “proper” proof is beyond the scope of this article, but I’ll try to give you an intuitive explanation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When doubling the size of the array, we have to copy some number of elements (let’s call that number &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newly allocated, bigger array will have &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; “free spots”, so next &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; insertions will be fast.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The “cost” of copying the array is proportional to &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt;, but it is “amortized” over &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;x&lt;/code&gt; insertions. Thus, average cost “per insertion” is constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you’re still confused (or curious), you might want to watch this excellent video on Coursera:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;hey-but-what-about-this-extra-memory-we-reserved-what-happens-when-we-remove-elements&quot;&gt;Hey, but what about this extra memory we reserved? What happens when we remove elements?&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Good question. Imagine a full dynamic array with a capacity of 10 000 elements. Now, let’s suppose we remove 9 000 elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we don’t resize the underlying array, our data structure will only use 10% of the allocated space. That’s not good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Just as we increased the capacity of the array when adding elements, we should reduce the capacity when removing elements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, when the size of a dynamic array drops below a certain percentage of it’s capacity, we move all elements to a new, smaller array.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like when adding elements, just the other way around!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;but-i-always-just-added-and-removed-elements-without-think-about-any-of-those-things&quot;&gt;But I always just added and removed elements without think about any of those things!&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many high-level programing languages provide functionality of dynamic arrays “out of the box”. JavaScript engines do
&lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.msdn.microsoft.com/jscript/2008/03/26/performance-optimization-of-arrays-part-i/&quot;&gt;magic&lt;/a&gt; that allows programmer to add and remove elements from the array as he pleases. In Python, lists are implemented using &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.python.org/2/faq/design.html#how-are-lists-implemented&quot;&gt;dynamic arrays with some extra cleverness
added&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abstracting such details allows you to focus on solving the problem at hand and makes developing software easier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked about 3 fundamental data structures: arrays, lists and dynamic arrays.
But we barely scratched the surface.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next part we will compare those data structures. We will investigate
operations supported by them, and their time complexity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 Let’s talk about two fundamental data structures everyone needs to know: arrays and linked lists.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Interview Preparations: Thread vs Process</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/thread-vs-process.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Interview Preparations: Thread vs Process" /><published>2017-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2017-12-29T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/thread-vs-process</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/interview-preparations/thread-vs-process.html">&lt;p&gt;Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code
works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts
can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 Let’s talk about a popular interview question: &lt;em&gt;“What are the differences between a process and a thread?”&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will assume that you have a basic understanding of how a processor works, and
how data is stored in memory. In particular, you should be familiar with &lt;strong&gt;CPU
registers&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gribblelab.org/CBootCamp/7_Memory_Stack_vs_Heap.html&quot;&gt;stack, and
heap&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before we try to make any comparisons, we need to get a solid grasp of relevant
terminology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we need to understand what a &lt;strong&gt;computer program&lt;/strong&gt; is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A computer program is a set of instructions that can be executed by the CPU&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A program is a static entity: it might be an executable file located somewhere
in the file system. When you double-click the icon or run a command in the
terminal, the program is loaded into RAM, and then it becomes a &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt; is a program in execution.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, if you run a program multiple times there will be a few processes running
simultaneously, all corresponding to the same program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Why do we need processes?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each process contains everything required to run (or restart) the program:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Address space&lt;/strong&gt; — an abstraction for all memory available to that process.
Address space contains program’s code and data required to run the program
(static data, heap, and stack).&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;One or more &lt;strong&gt;threads of execution&lt;/strong&gt; (I’ll explain that term in detail later)&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Set of &lt;strong&gt;OS resources&lt;/strong&gt;, for example opened files or network connections&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;figure class=&quot;class1 class2&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn-images-1.medium.com/max/1000/0*30_qL_hReOgXKmMU.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;&lt;em&gt;A photo of a thread. I’m very funny.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each process contains a single or multiple &lt;strong&gt;threads of execution&lt;/strong&gt;. If a
process has a single thread, only one action can be performed at a time. If a
process has multiple threads, it can perform multiple actions at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thread is a sequence of instructions that can be executed independently from
other code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;A Thread (or a thread of execution) is a sequence of instructions that can be
processed by a single CPU core.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Imagine that you are planning a programming conference: you should create a plan
of the event: who will be giving talks, what will they be about, and so on
(that’s our &lt;strong&gt;program&lt;/strong&gt;). The big day comes, guests arrive and our event is
taking place (our &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt;). During the conference, many talks (&lt;strong&gt;threads&lt;/strong&gt;)
might happen at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;threads&quot;&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Threads&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each thread contains all information necessary to execute it’s code. We need to
keep track of 1) which part of the program is currently being executed and 2)
what is currently stored in memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s why each thread has its own &lt;strong&gt;program counter&lt;/strong&gt; (a pointer that indicates
which instruction will be executed next), &lt;strong&gt;CPU registers&lt;/strong&gt;, and a &lt;strong&gt;stack&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threads within the same process share all other memory segments:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;heap&lt;/strong&gt; — containing dynamically allocated variables&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;text segment&lt;/strong&gt; — containing program’s code&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;data segment&lt;/strong&gt; — containing global or static variables&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other system resources such as currently opened files are shared as well. If a
file is opened, all threads can use it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Okay, but we didn’t really answer the question — what are the differences
between a thread and a process?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most significant, practical difference is in how processes and threads
communicate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a multithreaded process, &lt;strong&gt;threads share memory&lt;/strong&gt;. Thus, many threads can
access and modify the same memory, which may lead to bugs that are very
difficult to find.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Processes don’t share memory in this way, they have to use &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Inter-process_communication&quot;&gt;inter-process
communication&lt;/a&gt;
instead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Creating a process is fairly resource-intensive. It is generally more efficient
to use a single multi-threaded process than to spawn multiple single-threaded
processes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To summarise:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A &lt;strong&gt;process&lt;/strong&gt; is a program in execution. A &lt;strong&gt;thread&lt;/strong&gt; is a sequence of program’s
instructions that can be executed by a single CPU.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;A process might contain many threads. Those threads will share most of memory
segments. &lt;strong&gt;Threads may access and modify shared memory.&lt;/strong&gt; Processes use
&lt;em&gt;inter-process communication&lt;/em&gt; instead.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html">Modern programming languages abstract a lot of low-level details of how our code works. Nonetheless, a good understanding of underlying computer science concepts can help you write better code… and pass technical interviews 😉 Let’s talk about a popular interview question: “What are the differences between a process and a thread?”</summary></entry></feed>